[siren blares]
[music]
[Peter] Good morning, guys,
here in Flint, Michigan,
a place that I'd say nationwide
has a pretty tough reputation.
But it's also the place that created
General Motors and a booming middle class
peaking at
about 200,000 people back in 1960.
Since then
the population is less than half of that.
So what is it like here now in Flint?
What are the stories on the streets?
Today, we're going to dive in
and get a better look
of what this place is all about.
Let's do this.
Downtown Flint,
gotta say this place immediately
has a feel of its own.
Beautiful old bones here.
Look at this theater.
The Capitol Theater.
Looks like it's still happening here,
which is great.
Just a testament to the times
when this place was thriving.
It wasn't Detroit, it was Flint
for General Motors in the beginning.
And so all these jobs came in here
and built up a city
around basically one industry.
But Flint, I gotta say, first impressions,
you're seeing a hodgepodge
of things going on here.
You see there's some energy
being put into this town.
Look at this beauty.
And guys, you're not going to believe
what I just pulled up on my phone.
Right here, this very place,
and maybe that's why the road's closed.
Last night, a shooting.
An actual murder down here.
Someone was killed I believe.
One dead, one hurt,
in Downtown Flint shooting.
Saginaw and First,
which is this exact area.
So I was just about to say
how great it feels.
But it's a mixed bag.
I'm sure as we'll get into all day today.
Hey, the shooting
was right here last night, huh?
I think so. I don't know.
I briefly saw it on the news.
I wasn't here.
-Is it that bad downtown right now?
-I don't know.
Normally, I've been downtown
plenty of times.
It's like,
I don't ever really feel in danger.
But you know,
there's lots of criminals in Flint.
So anything
could really happen theoretically.
I don't ever feel like in danger.
-Stay away from shit like that.
This city is f*cked.
They may try to make it look ritzy
down here, but it's f*cked up.
-How so?
-Because it's Flint f*cking Michigan.
Because the politicians pocket money
and the police pocket money.
And they don't fix the real problem.
They don't go to the source of the problem
which is the rich motherf*ckers.
They just don't give a f*ck.
-You're not feeling Flint these days?
No, I've lived here my whole life.
I was born at Hurley in '86.
-Okay, was it worse
back in the day or is it worse now?
-No, it's way worse now.
-Seriously?
I could walk anywhere when I was a kid.
-Now it's worse?
-Yeah.
-Okay. Take care, man.
40 years old, you know. It's worse.
So if you're new to my videos…
You realize I like to
talk to as many people as possible.
And so that's that man's opinion.
We get as many opinions as we can.
He could be 100% right.
I don't know. I'm not from here.
But the style here
is to get it through the locals.
Not through a mouthpiece.
Not through a politician.
But through what we come into.
We can see J London's fine men's apparel.
So you still got some of
these classic clothing shops.
That's old school for sure.
Got some statues over here.
A nice brick street.
Henry Ford Health.
University of Michigan Flint.
Didn't expect to see that down here.
Look, we got a Barnes and Noble downtown.
Fantastic.
And there's not much street life
so far today.
It is a Sunday.
So maybe the Flintstones sleep it in
or just don't come downtown.
-[siren blares]
-Not sure.
Car coming pretty quickly.
[siren continues]
[motorcycles pass]
So we're just going to peel off
the main drag here.
See if we can find some life.
[woman] I was sitting in a cafe.
I was sitting in that coffee house.
And I'm like,
I know this guy from somewhere.
-Are you a Flintstone?
-No, I'm from Saginaw.
I watch you all the time.
-Thank you. What's your name?
-Jennifer Marks.
-Okay, I'm making a video on Flint.
-What are you doing here?
-I come down here all the time.
-Do you like it?
-Oh, yeah. I love it here.
My daughter dances in the Philorica dance
at the Institute for Performing Arts.
My sister and me used to work
down here in the Flint area.
So we kind of just
always came down here to Flint.
And just like the restaurants.
Before it was…
They didn't have all this.
-What do you mean the main drag?
They didn't have all the businesses
like the Cork on Saginaw.
And everybody just started
building businesses down here.
-Okay. So you're saying
it's going in a good direction.
It's going in a good direction.
Kind of like Detroit is.
-Detroit's nice now.
-Yeah.
I'm surprised. That's where I'm staying.
Downtown Detroit is nicer
than a lot of cities right now.
-Yeah. There's a renaissance.
-Clean, nice.
Don't want to get dark,
but just gotta point the obvious.
There was a murder last night.
Someone was shot and killed.
So that stuff's happening.
There's still crime here.
Yeah. There's still crime.
-So you're not coming
and hanging out at nights?
No, not in a crime area.
Okay. So you come in during the day,
do your thing.
-Your daughter comes, does her dancing.
-Yeah.
-And you go to a restaurant and go.
-Okay.
I just come down here.
As a video maker
I could show just that first guy
and just look for those stories
or I could show just that woman
and look for her stories
and really nail down
on one side of things.
But that's not my style.
It's not what I want to see online.
And that's why you're here most likely.
You don't want that either.
Now what I run into is what I run into.
So that's the best I can give you.
Here we have a Flint alleyway.
It's cool.
They're letting the art flourish.
Here's another one.
That is awesome.
I've never seen that on power meters.
Someone painting them up.
Looks really nice.
Shout out to Angela Bower.
Love your style.
That is so cool.
Hey, they're trying here. I gotta say.
They're definitely trying here in Flint.
What do we have here?
Local 432.
What's going on here at 432?
Right now we're doing a photo shoot
for John Hammon and his band.
-Is that a local band?
-Yes it is.
-Are they pretty good?
-Oh yeah.
It's between rock and country.
Kind of like a Bob Seger-ish
but a little bit more metal.
-Are we going to drop in
a slide guitar occasionally?
[chuckles] I don't know about tonight.
-You're a large?
-I'm a large.
-There you are, buddy.
-Thank you. I appreciate it.
This is actually John Hammon right here.
This is his band.
Okay. John Hammon Band.
I wish I had a third hand but I got you.
All right.
John Hammon
is like one side of the equation
and Streetlight Saints is the band name.
-Okay. So what's your take
on the music scene in Flint right now?
So people associate Flint
as being vehicle city.
-You know we're in GM town?
-Yeah.
The truth of the matter is we have
more musicians than we have shop rats.
This is a musical city.
Anything that you want.
If you want rap, we got Dayton Family.
If you want metal, we got Never The Crash.
We have Approaching Autumn.
If you want bluegrass music, there's the
entire Michigan Bluegrass Association
right here in Flint, Michigan.
-So people are coming to see music here?
Yeah. If they know about it,
people show up. It's beautiful.
Isn't that usually the case when you have
a town that's gone through rough times?
It gets cheaper and then the arts and
the creativity really start to flourish.
'Cause that's where the energy goes.
I'll agree to that.
-Or where do I have that wrong?
-No, it's not wrong.
I would say the music never stops.
The art never dies.
It just kind of goes through phases.
As older generations move up,
the new ones come in.
Which is one of the things
that we try to do. We elevate. We inspire.
We try to write some new stuff
for everyone that wants to hear it.
I'll play a country song
but we're going to play some metal too.
-Oh, my wife will like you for that.
Slipknot's her favorite band.
-I love Slipknot.
-Yeah.
She's sweet and nice, but then she goes
to Slipknot and starts headbanging.
-So it lets it out with the music, right?
-Yeah, dude.
Music is a universal thing
where it doesn't always happen
exactly the same every single show.
Everything is unique in the moment.
-Are you a Flintstone?
-I am.
How would you say 2026 Flint,
you've been through some rough times.
-Where is it at now?
-It's elevating.
-And it's going up, you think?
I think that we have a beautiful city that
every decade or so
kind of has a renaissance.
And right now,
there's a lot of people that are
absolutely dedicated to doing
what they can to make our city beautiful.
You see the murals.
The arches were gone for 30 years
and they brought them back.
-So local artists doing the murals?
-Yes. I don't know his name.
-Oh, shout out to him whoever he is.
-Yeah.
Many of you know me as a video maker,
but for the first time
I can say I'm a published author,
a New York Times bestselling author.
Your fellow Americans, if you love
what you're seeing behind the screen,
you're going to love the book 'cause
there's all sorts of stuff that's in here
that you're not gonna see on YouTube.
For example the time I was locked
out of my rental in Amish country
in my underwear
and having to navigate that world.
Which was quite challenging.
Or just all the moments that happen when
the power button's off
and getting deeper stories with people.
Just a lot of
my favorite videos, actually.
Some of the classics are in here,
but just with more history,
more thoughts, more reflection,
it's a deeper dive on the country.
And then the last chapter,
that's the one that's called
The Road Trip That Started It All.
And that's my origin story
and how I got into this crazy lifestyle
and wild career
of making videos across the country.
All sorts of little nuggets in there.
It's really a fun book.
I put a lot into it.
I think you're going to love it too.
Thank you all who've bought it so far.
For those still looking to buy it,
the quickest way is through Amazon.
That link is somewhere around here
or down below in the description.
If you want to support physical bookstores
like Barnes & Noble,
every Barnes & Noble in the country
is carrying your fellow Americans,
or indie bookstores,
many of them, not all, but many are.
And if they don't have it, you can ask
and they'll order it for you.
You're gonna love it. It's a great gift.
It's a great coffee table book.
It's a lot of fun.
It's our story of this beautiful country.
Now back to the video.
We got a big shout out to John Hammon.
Didn't hear his music,
but just had that musician vibe to him
where I bet he's really good.
And he gave us our time.
So go check him out.
Look at that. Keeps on going.
How are you guys doing?
-Are you guys from here?
-Yeah.
-How's it going?
-Going good.
-I like Flint.
-Yeah?
It's my favorite.
I grew up in Beecher though.
-That's like a district.
-Okay.
We always competed against Flint schools.
Beecher schools is more suburb.
-Is this apartments?
These are lofts. There's only six units.
-No way.
-Yeah. They like 2,300 square feet.
The rent here is cheaper
than like big cities or wherever.
-Cheaper than Detroit?
-Yeah.
-Can you get a place for like a thousand?
-I would say Mich… No!
I mean you wouldn't want it if it's…
-So a good loft around here
is like $1,500, something like that?
More. Well…
-Wow.
Not cheap. All right.
Good luck, you guys. Take care.
We have the First National Bank of Flint,
from its founding in 1864
through its closure in 1933
during the Great Depression.
The First National Bank played
a significant role
in its home city's development.
-Bank vault, right? Is that what this was?
-That's the bank vault.
All right. That is cool. Look at that.
The Flintstone's money
would go in here and a lot of it.
'Cause they seemed to
have it back in the day.
And they've turned this into
a beautiful restaurant hotel.
And we're way early,
so that's why there's nobody here.
-Is it Genesee or Citizens Bank?
-Genesee Bank.
-Genesee Bank back in the day?
It opened up in 1878,
but it was across the street.
-Okay, so it was
the lumber money at that time
coming here
before the auto money I believe.
Oh, yeah.
The deposits would all go in
behind that door over there.
The man used to look out at the bank.
-Oh, right up there?
-For the funny business.
-Looking for the funny business.
Growing up here,
this was the greatest place to grow up.
Yep.
-Okay, you caught the tail end
of all its prosperity
when you were growing up?
Let's see. When did things start changing?
Probably in the mid-'80s.
-Yeah.
-When General Motors started moving out.
Moving down south?
The the crack epidemic hit
in the early to mid-80s.
Things got a little bad for a while.
-So GM leaves, the jobs leave,
things go downhill, the drugs come in.
White flight,
folks move out to the suburbs.
I just watched a video,
the exact same thing happened in Detroit.
They had a place called Bottom.
-Yeah.
They had Paradise City, and then
they cleared it out for a freeway.
I just watched it.
They showed the man where
they named the county after him.
Even with 475,
the highway that came through here
tore up a lot of communities like…
-St. John's.
-Okay.
-So you saw at the tail end of that
at its worst point
and now it's coming back a bit?
I think it is. Yeah.
I mean, I think
it still has its issues.
The water crisis didn't help.
-Is that fixed now?
-Oh, yeah.
-You guys are good on that front?
They just announced that
they have replaced the last water line
that needed to be replaced.
-Yeah.
-It's all been done.
I read 11,000 lines, $100 million,
something crazy like that.
So everyone gets clean water now?
Yeah. I feel safe drinking the water.
-Okay.
-And using the water.
-That wasn't fun though,
back in the day, huh?
No, it was not.
We didn't know who to trust,
what to trust.
We still have people who say,
"I don't want to drink the water."
Yeah, trust takes time to get back.
Yeah. It takes time.
They're taking this old Art Deco building
and putting new windows in.
So maybe apartments
and these storefronts,
a lot are empty, some are open.
-How you doing, sir?
-How you doing?
-They doing apartments here?
What are they doing?
It's just an empty building, man.
They're not trying to rent it or nothing.
-You from Flint?
-Yeah.
-How's it going?
-Okay.
-Going okay? You doing all right?
I've been homeless a couple of months.
My dad passed away June 11th.
-I'm sorry, man.
-I've been out here for a while now.
-Is there nowhere for you to go?
-No, everything's full right now.
-It's full?
A lot of homeless people right now?
I'm sorry about your father.
Yeah, it sucked.
He came home from the hospital
and he was gone in his wheelchair.
Wow. So where are you staying now?
I sleep on the concrete up at the church.
GHS is trying to work with me.
-Who's GHS?
-Genesee Health System.
Okay. So someone's trying to help you.
That's cool.
-All the best, sir.
-All right. Thanks.
-Take care.
All right, guys. We're going to go
north of the river here in Flint
where I was told is the roughest hood.
So some quick numbers for you.
The median household income is $38,000.
Across the US it's $81,000.
One third of the population
lives below the poverty line,
and the murder numbers are,
the homicide numbers are pretty high.
Roughly 60 per 100,000.
Which puts Flint
above Memphis, that's per capita,
Chicago, Detroit,
but not St. Louis.
St. Louis seems to get the top place.
I guess, in recent years.
The homicides take place,
I'm sure, all over the city,
but they're gonna happen
in zip codes like this,
where it is the hood,
as everyone in town told me.
Said careful up there on the north side.
And what I've always found in the hood is
most people are friendly and cool,
and they're actually happy
you're interested in them.
They want to tell their stories.
And then there are
some downright sketchy people
that you don't want to be around.
So you always gotta
keep flowing and moving,
especially when you got a camera
and look like me in these parts.
So, yeah, we'll scope around.
I want to show you some of this
real estate because Flint's real estate
is rock bottom as far as prices go.
And I found a couple houses
on Zillow last night
where if someone wants
to get a home for the price of rent,
say for half a year most places,
you can have a home in Flint.
Now, do you just want to
put up with the rough part of Flint.
So, we're at the fire station,
honor, serve, and unite.
Again, the murals
just keep on giving in this town.
It is quite cool.
And so we're getting out of
this place where you gotta remember,
200,000 people were here at one time.
And so a lot of these lots
were probably homes at one time,
and they've just leveled them over time.
So you get these big open places
in cities like Flint or Detroit.
In Detroit they're doing a lot of gardens
which I find to be quite cool.
Look at this, though. You have
that remnants of a thriving economy.
And then you can just see how things
just sort of fell out here
and rubble.
Look at that chimney.
It is formerly a house, obviously.
And then some people raising
their families and doing all right.
So definitely a different America out here
compared to most of it.
And this is what makes
interesting content.
Unfortunately, middle-class suburbs
aren't that interesting.
Neighborhood after neighborhood
and that is what a lot of America is
but places like this
where you have these architectural gems
and then you see the plywood,
and then you see the blight.
And it's a bit sketchy.
So it makes it interesting.
And so I'll get comments
in this video saying
"America is over it's all done.
It's all falling apart and over."
Well, no, it's not.
There are plenty of
thriving places in this country.
Everything is going through a cycle.
Flint, especially,
is an extreme form of that, right?
Where it had its high point.
So let's try to find some people here.
This is actually cooler
than I thought it would be
as far as buildings and architecture.
You just have roads like this
where they have barricaded it off.
So no one can drive down them.
We've got a big park here.
You know, from what I'm seeing in Flint,
there is money here coming into the city
as far as the YMCA, big parks.
I can't speak credibly on it
because I don't live here
but even in America's roughest places,
there are always resources coming through.
Now, I'm not saying
it's fixing the problem.
And quite often money is the easy part.
That's what's wild. You think money
and buildings will change a place.
It's like, how do you bring up
people's sense of purpose and pride?
The pride that comes from
work and earning money
and supporting your family.
That's a tougher challenge, right?
You can throw
all the money you want at something.
But if the mentality is not there
then it's hard to fix.
And I'm not saying the mentality
is not here. I don't know anyone here.
But I'm just saying in other parts of
the country that are pretty down and out
there's a lot of cycles
of poverty and rough upbringings.
and that is the heavy lift.
The easy lift is actually buildings.
It takes all of it though really.
Okay, we're coming up to this house soon.
Okay, here it is.
A bit of a fixer-upper
but you won't believe the price.
You're getting a fair amount
of land there, a nice corner lot.
I don't know
if that's going to be fixed up.
Had its day.
But here we go. Two beds, two baths.
992 square feet.
With the price of $6,500.
That can be yours.
And I'm sure you could buy
this one for maybe even less.
And there you go.
Your Flintstone dream
comes true on the cheap.
Now these were all GM workers
or a business aligned with GM.
There you go.
A month of rent basically,
in a decent place in New York City
will get you into Flint.
Now, do you want to live in Flint
is another question
and what are you going to do here?
But hey, there you go.
You want cheap real estate?
There it is.
Here we have a much nicer one.
Four bed, two bath, 2,400 square feet.
This one is going for
many multiples more at $80,000.
There you go.
What's that mortgage payment
with the taxes here and insurance?
I'm going to guess 800 bucks,
something like that.
[Peter] So you work for USPS
and you moved out here, cheap rent.
[woman] Yeah, I pay $850 a month.
[Peter] $850?
[woman] Yeah, but with my credit,
the house was about $80,000.
I think it would have been $1,000
I would have had to come up with.
-Okay.
-And I had it.
I mean I still do
but you know what I mean?
It's just to qualify for the program
you have to have six-something or better.
My credit took a flaw.
-I have a truck in that garage, so…
-Okay.
You know.
-But thanks for what you do.
-Oh, thank you.
-I like USPS.
You guys never mess up for me at least.
Well, mail's gonna be behind a little bit.
They fired the company that was
picking up the mail just so you know.
-In Flint?
-Yeah.
-Oh.
-So there's going to be delayed mail now.
-So you're running out here
'cause it's cheap? It works for you?
Yeah. I'm a single mom, so…
-Okay.
-You know what I mean?
How's the energy in the hood here?
People cool?
Is it much danger and much violence or?
No. This street is pretty quiet.
-This street's quiet?
-Yeah.
If you go down,
it depends on what block you're on.
Some people usually keep to their self
and they keep to their self.
I don't have any in commons with them.
They're quiet.
And that's what I wanted.
I just wanted I keep to myself
and I just wanted peace, so…
-Okay. Okay.
And I think there's a lot of older people
that stay around here, you know.
Old people from back in the day of GM?
-Maybe.
-Maybe. Okay.
Wow.
There's the old man
over there at the corner.
He was just outside
cutting his yard, you know.
That's cool.
Let me ask you this, as a single mother
making what you make at USPS,
living out here,
can you pay all the bills okay?
Or is it tight?
I get by.
You have to be smart.
You have to budget.
I have teenagers,
so they're wanting a lot of things.
We're just getting by.
The water is actually with that
type of size house, it's not that bad.
-The what? I'm sorry?
-The water.
-The water bill isn't high.
-Your water bill's not high?
It's under $100.
-I mean, that's a pretty amazing deal.
If you can get your credit straight.
Would you love to live here?
It might be or whatever…
Regardless, I know what I'm looking for.
Like foundation, roofing.
When it comes to buying,
I know what I'm looking for.
And I'm not going to settle
until they fix it.
I won't buy until things are fixed.
-Smart. 'Cause that stuff gets expensive.
-Yeah. I know.
Trust me. I already know. [chuckles]
Thank you. All the best.
Good luck with everything.
-Thank you.
[Peter] Give credit where credit's due.
They're really trying here.
Look at all these flower planters.
You can see around here.
Genesee County Preschool.
Actually quite a bit
of park area in Flint.
And this is the hood.
This is what I was told
was the rough part.
But even in this part of town,
look, all the murals up on the buildings.
And we got a blast from the past here.
An old phone.
For those that know, you remember
exactly how these numbers press
and how they're indented
and your finger goes into them.
And that feeling and that feeling.
And those who don't
will never experience that.
But that's how it was done
back in the day.
Looks like we've got
an old elementary or high school.
No longer.
You gotta think
what that does to the school system
when that many kids leave town.
Well, they just let it go
to this I guess.
Looks like a dumping ground now.
Geez.
All sorts of stuff back there.
That's awful.
You can see there's some fires lit.
And that's all across from
actually a nice looking playground.
[siren blares in the distance]
And you hear a lot of that in Flint.
The sirens.
You know, not a  good visual every day.
And how do you
teach people not to do that?
Because here's the deal.
If your dad does it
then you do it most likely.
No matter what that is.
Throwing trash on the ground
or how you treat servers at a restaurant.
It usually comes from the parenting.
So how do you change the cycle
so that's no longer?
You know, I can only go so far
as an outsider here.
I'm looking for people.
There are really no…
There's nobody
on the streets unfortunately.
Here we are, Bryant Elementary School.
School of Fine Arts.
Bryant Center has been properly looted.
And then the DG's come into town.
DG is everywhere.
[Peter] Look at you just styling.
Look at that. There we go.
So you thought through it.
You went glasses, to lipstick,
all the way through the dress.
There we go.
And those nails, those nails
might be weapons. Can I see those?
No, those are not weapons.
-What's your name?
-Cassandra.
Cassandra. Nice to meet you, Peter.
-Peter.
-Yeah. Nice to meet you.
What do you do?
I make videos all over the country.
-You do?
-And I look for cool locals to talk to.
Oh my goodness. That's amazing.
So what are the topic today
on this beautiful Sunday?
You know, there's no narrative to fill.
Just learn from the people.
-Go with the flow.
Are you from Flint?
So I'm originally from Louisiana,
Baton Rouge.
-Okay. You are? Nice.
-Yeah.
-What do you think of it up here?
Oh, I just think we need more
love and great hospitality here.
I think there's no unity here no more.
-Really?
-Yeah.
Like, when you go down South,
it's nothing but family,
and it's a lot of love.
People just come together.
No matter what race you are,
no matter if you're old, young,
everybody just gets together.
-You're not feeling that in Flint?
-I'm not.
-Really?
But, like, when we have events and stuff,
that's the only time
that we can get together.
And then when
we do have the events it's like
you got to be cautious
of how many young people is around you.
Because you're older
and you really don't want to,
you know, get shot up.
Or you don't want to be in
the midst of anybody's beef.
Because it's so young-minded these days.
The generation and the era now is just…
[scoffs]
-Right.
-I'm sorry.
-It's crude.
-Well, look. I run into
great young guys and girls all the time.
But, it's interesting.
In inner-city America,
there's no order anymore.
Before, like, say, Bloods and Crips,
there was order from the top down.
-Yeah.
-You didn't disrespect your OG.
-And we have no order.
-You stayed in line.
Now everyone's scared of
the 15-year-old with the gun.
-Yeah. That's what I'm saying!
-TikTok brain.
-That's what I'm saying.
-And they don't know the consequences.
They haven't fully developed
their brains, gotten good examples.
And then it's like
that's what you got to watch out for.
-And they have been traumatized.
-100%.
The upbringing has been
raised off of survival.
-Yeah.
-And no love, like…
-Yeah. Right.
-So, that has to change.
-It does.
-And that's not a money thing, either.
-It's not.
But it's more of, like, time and love.
Like you're saying. And nurturing.
-Yes, it is.
-Connection.
-But you seem like you got a lot of love.
-I do. I have a lot of love.
-You got kids?
-Yes, I do. I have two beautiful boys.
-Okay. Here?
-Seven and 12. Yes.
-Oh, good for you.
-And they're the light of my life.
Like they really made me grow
in so many different ways.
Like just when I first held my oldest,
it was like a new start for me.
A fresh start at life.
Like I knew some of the things
that I was doing like partying,
I had to change.
I had to change my mental.
And I just grew out of everything.
And now I am so refreshed
and rejuvenated now that I have children.
-That was priority
and everything else fell to the wayside.
-That's a choice of a parent.
-Yes, it is.
And it's a beautiful choice to make.
It is.
-How do you keep your kids
from getting into
the heavy, dark stuff out here?
Okay, so keeping them
involved in educational activities.
And my sons are in Christianity activities
throughout the church.
We do drives. We do picnics.
Anything to keep them
out of the streets and focus.
Basketball camp, summer camp.
I have thrived all year
to make sure
that I keep my kids
out of the streets and away from violence.
Anything that I can do positive,
lemonade stands to cookie stands,
we have done.
And we're going to keep doing it.
-Are you a single mother?
-So yes, I am a single mother.
-That's tough, huh?
-Well, it is tough.
But at the end of the day,
if you have Christ
or whoever positive that you are
praying to, you will get through it.
You will get through it.
-It makes you stronger too.
-Yes it does make me a lot stronger.
Because at the end of the day,
I want them to know
that when they get older,
their women, wives,
are supposed to be great people of society
and also lead them in a positive way.
You know, just like men are supposed to
lead their wives in a positive way.
So I think it's great to be
just great people all the way around.
I feel like whatever you show them,
that's what they're going to possess.
That's the type of characteristics
they're going to have.
Try to create a good example.
-So what's the solution to hoods
like this in Flint, across America?
-Well, I would say…
-What are your thoughts?
I would say just getting together
and wanting to do
a whole sweep of cleaning up,
doing projects together,
and just making our side great again.
'Cause that's pride, right? When you
keep your place clean and it looks good.
Yeah.
And so if a kid grows up
and there's trash everywhere like here,
they don't know.
-Right?
-Yeah, right. That's it.
They're not going to feel pride
and there's broken windows theory.
If you see broken glass and trash,
you're going to feel more trash.
That's it. It's going to keep multiplying.
That's it.
So if you give them
the clean mind state of,
"Hey, let's go out here
and do a neighborhood clean up."
Then the kids will be more like,
"Wow, we gotta keep
our environment clean."
But if you just throw trash
in front of them,
I mean, what do you think
they're naturally going to do?
I could imagine if you're a kid here,
like Miss Queen said,
you better hope you have someone
like Miss Queen getting you into sports,
into activities, into camps.
If you're into religion.
Because
the other side of things here is just like
bad influences
turning you on to drugs, crime,
murdering people.
And then once you go down that road,
it's very hard to come back from it.
Though I've seen that happen.
I've seen…
I've met people that did their time.
Prison, came out the other side
and became productive members of society.
That does happen.
But it's a hard slog.
Better not to go down
that road in the first place.
Let's just cruise
another street here or two
and then we'll go over to
the nice part of town.
Which I heard there is
a nice part of town in Flint
where the upper level managers
for GM lived back in the day.
I don't know who lives there now,
but I'm sure it was like the attorneys,
the accountants, the doctors,
people with bigger salaries.
And even in a small city like Flint,
you can live in your own bubble here.
Where where we're going
I'm sure they never come over here ever.
And the same, they're not
coming from here over to there.
Almost like parallel universes.
But they're doing a good job.
I will give Flint credit
for all the mowing
and all of these open spaces
which I'm sure were houses like that.
They're keeping maintained.
I'll give them credit.
So good job Flint on that front
because this would just all grow up.
Actually just turn into forest, I think.
-[woman] This is some of the ribs.
-[Peter] Oh yeah.
-This is pro.
-Brisket.
-I'll do brisket. Thank you.
-Yeah.
Try the tips next time.
Now we're only open until
September 4th, Labor Day.
That's our last day of the season.
-Oh.
-We're seasonal.
-Okay. What do you do after that?
Teaching.
-You're a teacher?
-Yes.
-Thank you.
Yes, thank you.
-I'm all over the country
and the story I hear the most
is teachers leaving unfortunately.
I know they are.
I'm a preschool teacher, so I work closely
with the kindergarten teachers.
-Okay.
And they are tired.
Kindergarten teachers are very tired.
-The kindergarten teachers are tired?
We try our best as preschool teachers
to prepare them for kindergarten.
Okay. So how is it going
for you teaching right now?
-Oh, it's going wonderful.
-That's cool.
It's been 28 years. I thank God.
And without him, I couldn't do it.
-God guides you through everything?
-He does.
Even when they are struggling
or they have behaviors,
I know where my help comes from.
-You're trying to
teach them social and what?
Emotional.
Because if they can't do that,
they can't learn.
If they cannot learn
how to control their behaviors,
or how to problem solve,
or how to calm themselves down,
social, emotional,
you know, instead of throwing stuff,
instead of using profanity,
instead of, you know,
if they can't do that, they can't learn.
All that ABCs and one two threes,
and all that comes after that.
They have to know
how to interact with each other.
[Peter] So Pat's got it all laid out here.
I can't put the camera on it because
it's her trade secret that nobody knows.
-Which keeps people coming back, right?
-Yes.
Oh, yeah. I see what you're doing.
Yeah.
-That's a good trick.
-Thank you.
-What's your take on Flint?
Do you love Flint or…
I do. I do.
I love the people here.
I love my community.
I'm proud of my community.
We do have a lot of neighbors
that they take care of their property.
You're still going to have some
that don't, but there's a lot that do.
I moved here in 1990 from Tennessee.
-Okay.
I still have a lot of
my Southern roots, you know.
I like to speak to people.
-Yeah, I can see that.
A lot of northerners don't like to speak,
but if they give me eye contact,
I'm going to say hello.
-Ms. Pat, you seem like
an optimistic, happy person.
What do you have to say
to your fellow Americans right now?
We need to love on each other
and respect one another.
We do.
And we need to pray
for our leaders that God will
give them the wisdom
and knowledge to lead us correctly
according to God's will
and not their will.
That's what we need.
-There we go. That's the final product.
We couldn't show the process.
-Lots of love in there.
-Lots of love.
All right. I can't wait to try this.
Thank you.
There we go. Look at that.
Ms. Pat's special brisket.
It's got a lot of sauce going on here,
but that meat is very tender.
It's going to be messy
and you just got to jump in.
Mmm. That is fantastic.
There we go. There's a lot here.
Mmm.
Very tender meat.
World-class barbecue.
-Ms. Pat, you're the best.
-Thank you.
Yeah. Appreciate it.
-Have fun with school.
-Yes. Yes.
[Motown music]
Wow. Look at this grand old place.
Vines are taking it over.
And now the homes are
getting a lot nicer up here on the hill
across from that massive Catholic school.
Okay, here's the one I was looking for.
This one's for sale.
Tudor Revival.
Four beds, six baths, 5,153 square feet.
for $550,000.
Look at that beauty.
And it's got a pool in the back I believe.
And up here you just have
well, the other side of the tracks,
that's for sure.
This is also Flint.
And these are beauties.
And I'm sure this part of town is
pretty safe and quiet back in the day.
And I'm sure it was the GM higher level
management that lived up here.
That Catholic school
is absolutely massive.
So I'm sure a lot of the kids were
going there. Maybe they still are.
And you just have
a different Flint up here.
It's just right at
the top of a little hill.
And then it dead ends here.
But it's just that one little zone
that is really nice.
And then we come off the hill
and we're back into it.
[Peter] All right, guys.
We got super lucky.
And meeting some fans of the channel.
-Local Flintstones, right?
-Yes.
Flintstones that are, what,
sixth generation?
My children are five now.
Okay.
And you know the automotive history here.
-And we're gonna cruise for a little bit.
-Absolutely.
All right. We scored
'cause my historical knowledge,
you know, it's reading up online.
But not really understanding
'cause I didn't grow up here.
So we have Dean.
-And we got Jens, right?
-Yep.
-Jens. All right.
[Dean] I saw the ghost
of what they built in the post-war era.
The structures and the organizations
that they created
to live the best life that
they possibly could after a world war.
Right? There was reason to celebrate,
to look to the future.
There was reason to
gather together as a community.
And build something amazing.
And they did that.
[Peter] Right.
GM got in on the war effort, right?
-Yes, they did. Sure.
-Okay.
-The Hellcat was built here, right?
On this street about five miles behind us.
At the former Cadillac plant
they built tanks.
They tested tanks.
So a lot of tanks that were developed
for the war were developed
literally just a few miles
from where we sit.
All of this was General Motors.
-Oh, all of this was GM's?
-[Jens] Everywhere you look.
-All of this landscape out here was GM.
[Jens] It was
what you would call Buick City.
It was a complex of
28-plus huge industrial-sized buildings.
And we're gonna show you some of it.
-To give it a perspective and scale,
there were 30,000 people
employed at Buick City at one point.
Way up to that water tower,
past that water tower,
all of this was factory.
Where literally steel and leather
and wood went in one end.
And cars came out of the other end.
-Okay. What are these now?
What are these little utility trucks?
Who knows? I know that there's
a company called Racer Trust that owns…
-These are Chevys.
-…the property.
GM has nothing to do with
all those in the electric…
-Yeah, these are the electric Chevys.
GM has nothing to do with this anymore.
-So in your younger years this was
all a factory and it was just booming.
-That's correct.
-And everyone was involved?
Everyone in town?
Pretty much. Yeah. And this was
just one of probably 22 facilities.
Maybe not this large,
but large enough to support
Buick, Olds, Pontiac, Cadillac, Chevrolet.
-So what was the average wage?
Like, so those times the wife
was staying home with the kids, right?
You had a house, you had a car.
The equivalent would be in the
neighborhood of $70,000 to $90,000 today.
Today's money.
Sometimes two people
worked in these factories.
-But houses were way cheaper, right?
-Actually houses are cheap here now.
-I think they're still pretty cheap.
-Then everything picked up and left
in the 70s, early 80s.
-Isn't that pre-NAFTA?
-Pre-NAFTA. Correct.
So where did it go?
Well, it didn't go to Mexico or Canada.
And General Motors had already
established ventures in Mexico and Canada.
Originally, they went to
Arlington, Indiana,
-Missouri, Arlington, Texas, I should say.
-Okay.
Buffalo, New York.
Outward, away from the Rust Belt.
-What was the catalyst?
Why did they leave?
It's really hard to say
because they built the infrastructure,
the power systems,
the water systems, the rail systems,
to support basically what amounts to,
between Saginaw and Detroit,
a massive manufacturing megacenter.
My belief is workman's rights,
the expectation of wages.
When the riots that happened
throughout the Midwest,
especially in Detroit and Flint happened,
I think some of those people,
some of the white-collar management layer
of not just General Motors,
but every manufacturer,
they walked onto their factory floors
and realized if these guys decide that
they've had enough of us, we're finished.
-[laughs]
-Okay.
I think they moved out quickly.
And they didn't just move the jobs.
They moved themselves
and they moved the jobs.
-Okay. So does that explain
when I'm coming from Detroit to Flint…
-…I'm in the suburbs that are really nice.
-Very nice.
And I see big factories out there
in the suburbs that look really nice.
-Yes.
-And so they just decentralized?
Yes, they did.
They pulled out of the cities because,
if I'm getting this right,
they saw this as somewhat volatile.
-I think so.
-Or that's up for argument.
That's up for debate.
During the Great Migration,
it wasn't only this city
that enjoyed the effort and labor
of people from the South.
Yeah.
It was all of the manufacturers
including the whole constellation
of industries
that support the auto industry.
Well, that's why they all came north,
because the jobs were here.
And who wouldn't?
Technology was getting better
in the South with cotton, right?
Needed less labor and those jobs
paid poorly I believe.
So why not come up,
work for one of the big three,
make good money, get health insurance?
Were they discriminated against? Yes.
-Yes, they were.
-Okay.
Where we left, when we crossed that river…
Yeah.
People of color
didn't come down to where we're driving.
-Really?
-No.
-So I went to the nice part,
which is sort of to the right here,
and I went up to these nice homes.
-So it was totally segregated?
-At that time, yes.
-And when did those times end?
They didn't really end until really around
the year that I was born, '67 to '72.
-Okay.
And I don't think that
people of color felt comfortable
traveling freely all over this area.
Okay. So it was really a segregated city.
And the reason I say that
is because I literally grew up
the only White kid in
a Black neighborhood not a mile that way.
-I was the only White kid.
-No way. How was that?
It was great honestly.
I was…
I think I was treated worse
when I hung out with White kids. [laughs]
I was welcomed.
I was made to feel important.
I was tolerated.
They were patient with me,
and I had a good experience.
-You weren't getting beat up?
-No, didn't happen.
When I was a little kid, I got…
Yeah, sure.
I'm a little nerdy kid with glasses.
I did get bothered.
But I would have
gotten bothered anywhere.
Once you come a certain age,
probably around middle school,
that stuff kind of ends.
So that ended, right?
And those became my people.
Those became my friends.
So I was raised around people
who were born prior to 1900.
So those folks lived discrimination.
-They knew no other way.
-Yeah.
My next door neighbor and another man
basically founded the concept of
what became
the model for public transportation
that helped stop that.
That way, a lady who cleaned houses
on the south side of the river
didn't have to walk five miles home.
She could get on a bus,
unmolested, and get home.
They created that.
In just a few minutes, two more lights,
you'll find basically
the birthplace of the modern union.
-The modern labor union?
-Correct.
-UAW?
-UAW.
And your father worked for GM, right?
-My dad did. Yes.
-Okay.
My grandfather did
and my great-grandfather did.
Oh, wow. Okay.
My great-grandfather
started at Buick in 1906.
My grandfather came back from World War II
and entered into his career.
Okay.
And my father entered in 1964
and he was drafted.
And something about his time in the Army,
when he came back from the Army
he wanted nothing to do
with General Motors.
And it broke my grandfather's heart
because my grandfather felt
that in my father that he would realize
all of the executive dreams
that he didn't realize.
My dad and my grandfather and
my great-grandfather were management.
They were the enemies
of the lady we're about to meet.
But if you look here, this building
right here is the last remnant
of the offices of a massive facility.
I went to school
literally next door to this place.
So this is my middle school.
-No way.
-This is where I went to middle school.
-And it's abandoned.
Oh, that's too bad, huh?
It's just there's a lack of kids, right?
I mean, the population
is down more than half.
-Yep.
-And that's just what happened.
I wouldn't say it's bad
'cause that wasn't
the best place to be in the 70s.
It was a bedlam. it was bedlam.
There's a tavern here that has
quite a history, The Wooden Keg.
Many many folks partied here,
met their wives and husbands here.
-Right here?
-Yeah.
-At The Keg?
-Yep.
-So this is GM currently operating?
-Correct.
Okay so I thought in Flint all of that
had left but it's still happening?
-It's still here.
-Okay what are they making here?
This is mostly truck.
In fact this truck turning.
-That's coming out of this.
-Likely came out of that building.
So there are good
well-paying jobs in town right now.
-There's a few, sure.
-I mean that's a huge facility.
So okay, the people working in there,
are most of them living outside of Flint.
They're not living in Flint?
I would say probably if you put
a gun to my head and ask me how many.
-I won't do that.
-I would say probably less than 10%.
Okay less than 10% live in the city.
-So GM still has a huge footprint?
-Very much so.
Maybe it's like the Mon Valley
south of Pittsburgh.
-I know exactly what you mean.
-Some of those steel jobs are still there.
But they lives in the country side.
They don't live in the town anymore.
[Peter] I've seen Tonya Burns everywhere.
Does she have a chance?
-I'll let Jans answer that question.
Unfortunately I will say
our political system in this city is…
it's not, I'm not gonna say corrupt.
But what I'm gonna say is comical.
If you know anything about Eric Mays
or any of these guys? Oh man.
The city council
can't even almost have a meeting
without the police
arresting council members.
-Oh geez.
-That's all I'll say.
-So there's definitely some corruption.
-Oh, it's…
Okay, Peter,
this is what I'm most excited about.
There we go.
It means a lot to me specifically,
I will say.
My mother's grandfather,
my great-grandfather,
was an original sit-down striker.
Okay, so for those that don't know about
labor unions, UAW, sit-down strikers…
Sure.
-Union formed because workers felt like
they weren't getting enough, right?
One of the things that I can tell you,
my great-grandfather
reiterated to my grandmother
that she said in my childhood,
I remember specifically
was in a 12-hour shift,
pre-union, if you even
went to the bathroom, your job was gone.
-Whoa.
-So they wanted to go to the bathroom.
Other than that, yeah, right?
Benefits, they wanted the same thing
they saw the people in white-collar…
-When did that happen, 1937?
1937 is when it originally happened, yes,
and it lasted for 44 days.
During these 44 days,
the plant Fisher, that this took place at,
they cut the heat off, and it was
middle of winter, the heat was cut off.
They dealt with the Flint Police,
the state police, National Guard.
So the employees said we're not working
until you give us more rights.
Absolutely.
We're not leaving your factory
until you give us some sort of
worth of life, right?
These men had children
that they had to take care of.
This to me means everything.
My great-grandmother
died at 98 years old
and she remembered taking
my great-grandfather food.
Now this is depiction of the wives
breaking the windows to throw
their husbands food and clothes.
-Wow.
-If you look at this,
this is a depiction of the police
or authority figure in general.
I'm not going to name a name but
dragging the wives away from the windows
from feeding their husbands.
They had been in there
for 44 days, cold, hungry.
And if you go here and you look at this,
it's a small child
that was picketing while their father
was inside the plant.
Just fighting for
a chance to take care of them.
-One thing I read
that I found fascinating.
So we're talking after the depression.
Things are still rough
economically, right, In '37.
-Sure.
-Pre-World War II.
-Before things really ripped off.
-Yeah.
So Billy Durant
went from founding GM, right?
To spending his remaining year…
He went broke. $3 million gone.
He went broke trying to stop
the 1929 stock market crash.
He single-handedly tried to buy stock
and keep the market liquid.
And he tried to convince
other people to do it too.
Who absolutely thought he was a fool.
-So yeah, then he went broke
and he ended up his later years,
running a bowling alley
outside of town here in this timeline.
You have depression. Things go down.
Sure.
He's trying to
get people to buy stock, bring it back.
He goes broke.
-This happens.
-Yep.
And then the war kicks off
and this thing just goes to the moon.
-Yes.
-Yep.
It wasn't just General Motors,
Ford, or Chrysler.
It was the whole nation.
We fought and won the European Civil War.
We had…
think about it for a second, guys.
Europe didn't win the Civil War.
The World War I and II culmination,
the Americans did.
And the Soviets too, right?
And what happened at the end of the war?
The United States had the most clothes,
the most food,
by far the most cash, and the bomb.
-We just had…
-What a time to be alive.
We had the advantage of
not being destroyed like Europe.
-Peter…
-What a time to be alive.
Can I show you this?
This is one thing that…
And you know, my wife,
we've been together for 15 years,
but she's convinced
we have such a strong connection.
These bricks inside this rope,
they are the names of
all the original sit-down strikers.
The men who lasted
all 44 days within the plant.
Now I want to point this out.
Over here, Bert Christenson
is my great-grandfather, okay?
Now if we go to the right of this sign,
the name Reese Easter,
that is my wife's great-grandfather.
So my great-grandfather,
my wife's great-grandfather
spent almost 100 years ago,
44 days together in a plant
fighting for their rights.
So we have deep ties here,
deep connections too.
-So this means a lot to you?
-To me personally.
I don't know how much
it means to my dad, but…
This is sacred ground for me.
If you think of it, a lot of the things
that we enjoy,
weekends, holidays off.
-So that's UAW, eight-hour work days?
-Yep.
This here is my grandmother. Carla.
Carla, that's who we're going to meet.
-No way, we're getting to meet her?
-Yeah, this is my grandmother.
She's still alive.
Her father was an original striker.
She retired.
-How old is she?
-She's in her eighties.
-Okay, where is GM now?
Is UAW still fully involved?
Oh yes.
-That car right there?
-Yeah.
If the union guys were here,
would have it towed.
That car should not be
in that parking lot.
-Oh, so to this day if someone has
a Japanese car, Asian car,
you're not popular?
Not at all.
Thank God they don't have a security guard
because them dudes
would kick us off this property.
-You were saying you didn't buy
a Buick for what reason? Why?
They fired my best friend.
Fired my best friend flat out.
And he was one of the smartest people
I've ever known in my whole life.
It's a shame that they let him go
because he helped them.
He was a benefit there.
He didn't cost them.
He was helping them. It's a shame.
-So just out of principle, you're out?
-I'm done.
-He thinks it's crazy.
He has two GM cars.
He doesn't have the same affliction
that I have, but I'm mad as hell.
So here we go.
[Peter] Okay, so the union stuff,
I don't know enough about it.
It makes sense from the outside.
Who doesn't want more worker rights?
I'm sure there's
a good argument against it.
And the one I was thinking of is,
look, the countries
that don't play by those rules,
if we're not protecting our industry,
then they can destroy us on price.
Like if Chinese cars tomorrow could come
to America we would kill a lot of our…
Not unless we reverse tariff, right?
In other words for every car that
General Motors or Ford or Chrysler builds,
the United States government
gives them X amount of dollars,
X percentage of the value
of the content of that vehicle.
Yeah.
We tried that in 2008. It was not popular.
Okay. But say from my recollection,
I could be off on that.
Germany taking our cars in,
they charged a 12% tariff.
Us taking cars from Germany
until recently, it was a 2% tariff.
-It wasn't even.
So they get
an advantage in a sense, right?
I would think so.
I know that's changed. I don't know
where tariffs are at right now.
It's impossible to follow it seems like.
-It's desperately confusing to me.
-It's desperately confusing.
-I have no clue.
-No.
But reciprocal, as in Germany
pays 12% for our vehicles,
we pay 12% for their vehicles.
that makes sense to me.
-Right? That's fair.
-I think…
No tariff in either direction
makes sense to me.
But look, if you have
the Chinese auto market being subsidized,
let's just say the government's
going to put money into it
'cause they're really good at business
and understanding how to win the game.
And so they realize
we want to get into the US car market.
We're gonna actually
subsidize whatever company.
We're gonna get them in,
US has no tariffs on the Chinese car.
Then the Chinese car,
because the quality's better,
the technology's there,
is going to decimate our auto industry.
So you need to have some sort of
protection, right?
Because their labor's cheaper,
the labor laws are different.
Like, make that make sense to me, Dean.
The Chinese vehicle, the ones that we see
that are so modern and so well-equipped,
so beautiful, and what, the top-level
Tesla compared to a BYD whatever,
there's a $60,000, $80,000 price
discrepancy,
it's because that vehicle
was built for that market.
I don't necessarily believe
that that same vehicle,
if you just uprooted it
and plopped it here in Flint, Michigan,
would fit this market.
I don't think that it's a fair…
-Yeah, but they would adjust it,
just like Nissan, right?
They would have to
because there's safety standards.
Yeah, but look at Nissan, or Toyota.
They don't have monster
pickup trucks in Japan, they adjust.
They figure out how to do it here
and they put their plants here.
Yes.
So, anyways, this is a long conversation.
No, no, no, it's fine.
I think that what you're getting at is
an equitable balance in trade.
Yeah.
And if we are operating at an imbalance
then that has to be corrected.
-Right, or these jobs go away.
-Yes.
[Peter] And then we get more Flints.
[Dean] The reality of the matter is
yes, it can happen here too
in your community,
in your city, in your town.
If I were to stand
on the corner of one of the streets
that we saw that looked terrible,
and said that in X number of years this is
all going to be gone, burned, blown up,
rotted, no one would have believed me.
They would have said I was crazy.
I don't want the key takeaway to…
Dean's saying that basically this is what…
Everything is gonna
go to hell in a handbasket.
Honestly, how many McDonald's jobs
are going to support a society?
-Yeah.
-Not a whole lot, right?
No offense, and I'm not knocking
anybody that works for McDonald's,
but it's not a future.
So we need skilled jobs.
We need living wages.
We need health care.
-We need childcare.
-So back to my point.
Then you need
those industries to have a chance
and if they get decimated
through global competition…
Correct.
Then you're gonna lose those industries
and you get more Flints.
Yes.
So that just makes logic to me,
and I don't understand it at a deep level.
-'Cause I haven't put enough time in it.
-Me either, honestly.
-Okay.
-I agree.
I'm with you, right?
And I don't want to sit here and say
that I know what the answers are.
-I do not.
-Yeah.
I can tell you
what the aftermath looks like.
Yeah, you can.
And it's not nice, huh?
Unfortunately, yes.
-We're outside of Flint proper right now?
-Correct.
It just totally changes
once you get out of the border.
-It's a hard line.
-You see it.
You see it and feel it.
-This is where Grandma lives?
-Yes, sir.
-And this is a couple miles from Flint?
-Yeah, maybe to my house
is probably two miles.
-Okay.
Grandma, this is Peter.
Peter, this is my grandma.
How you doing? Nice to meet you.
So Carla, we just saw your brick
out there at the memorial.
Oh, yeah.
It's been there for quite a while.
And Jens was saying you have stories.
-This here.
You want me to tell it, Grandma?
This here was a nail
that he would take a potato
and drive the nail into the potato
and put in the oven.
And the idea was so that the heat would
distribute evenly through the potato.
They had fires in the plant
during the sit-down.
They had to. It was wintertime.
-Oh, they were making fire in there?
-Yeah.
[Jens] Yeah. They cut off the heat.
-Cut off the natural gas.
-Cut off everything.
-So these were for…
this is just for food in there?
-Uh-huh.
-To warm the potatoes up?
Oh, wow.
What do you got there?
This is something they did
after Walter Ruther
died in the plane crash.
-Who's this?
He was the president
when the whole thing started.
-The UAW president? Okay.
-Uh-huh.
So your mother was getting food
through the window.
There was a lot of women
down there tossing food up
and getting clubbed by the police.
It was like a riot. It was a riot.
-So you grew up in Flint, obviously.
-Uh-huh.
-Did you love it?
Yeah, it was great back then.
Not so hot now.
So back in the day in Flint,
that theater, Capitol Theater, was busy.
-People walking the streets.
-Oh, yeah.
-I'm sure people dressed well, right?
-Mm-hmm.
Nice stores downtown.
-Nice stores downtown.
And since it was relatively a new city,
it would have been very clean
and sparkling, right?
Yeah, it was nice.
Beautiful place to grow up.
Real good schools.
[Jens] Irony there, right? To see.
'Cause we passed by the school
that was his that's dilapidated now.
And just one generation removed from that,
she's telling you that her schools
were amazing, right?
-You see what I mean?
-Right. And now how is it for yours?
Well, my kids can't even go to 'em.
They're just gone.
-Where do your kids go to school?
-A school in the next town over.
So right now we're in Grand Blanc.
And between Flint
and Grand Blanc is Burton.
-Okay.
Do you wish you grew up
at a different time in Flint history?
Uh, you know,
Flint was rough for me for sure.
-So you got it at its peak.
-Yeah.
Dean saw it at
the end of the peak in the decline.
And you just came in
to this world at the bottom.
The roughest part of time.
Okay. And then what's in your kid's
rough also? And we'll see where that goes.
So the problem
that I struggle with, parentally, right?
That's the biggest thing is
there's nothing here, right?
So every day that I spend here…
-In Flint?
-In Flint.
I feel like
I'm doing my own children a disservice
because the fact of the matter is, yes,
there's 5,000 GM jobs left in Flint,
but there's not much of anything else.
That just tells me automatically
my children will have to
venture out into the country
to find opportunity,
which puts them
farther away from me, right?
It doesn't keep them within town,
finding good jobs and benefits in town.
My grandkids aren't gonna be in town.
I'm highly aware of this
and that's one thing that I struggle with.
It's likely, to be honest,
it's probably within my three-year plan
to remove myself and children from Flint.
I don't have any other choice anymore,
you know?
I'll tell you how safe it was.
My brother and I, my brother, Peter,
we decided one day
to run away just for the day.
And we went a couple miles
up past Ballenger Highway.
And there was nothing up there.
We got back on our bikes about 5:00
and thought, oh, we're going to get it.
We got home and my folks
had been canning tomatoes all day
and they didn't know we were gone.
[Jens] Yeah, and you know,
talk about wages.
You mentioned it earlier
and my great-grandfather, her father,
he raised nine children.
My great-grandmother
was a stay-at-home mother.
They took vacations.
They had shoes.
They had… you know what I mean?
So he was able to provide
a life for nine children.
-How many children did you have?
-Four.
-Four. And did you stay home with them?
No.
I worked 30 years at AC Spark Club.
-Okay, when they were young,
you were working at AC Spark Plug.
Mm-hmm.
That's just something
they gave out on White Shirt Day.
-What's White Shirt Day?
-Something my mother and dad
came up with.
-Sit Down Strike Watch.
-That's the 75th anniversary UAW Watch.
-Okay, I couldn't read it.
Yeah, the White Shirt Day, that came up.
My mother and dad
were sitting there one night
trying to think of
what they could do to remember
all that they'd been through.
They came up with white shirt
because supervision,
they had to wear white because they were
so much better than the hourly people.
And my dad said,
we could all wear white and we'd be
just as good as they are. So they do.
I think it's
the 11th of February every year.
-So UAW still to this day
is very important for you?
Well, yeah, I get my pension. [laughs]
-But I heard you drive a Honda.
-Yeah.
-Tell us about that.
[Dean] There's more
union content in that Honda
than you'll find in a Chevrolet whatever.
-You serious?
-Yes.
And they're built here in the US too.
Yeah, they are down South.
We had union meetings
in the living room of our house.
For several years I think.
-Did you have any idea
how big this would become?
When you're having a union meeting
in your house and then the UAW is…
No, it didn't affect us kids.
We were too young.
-Oh, yeah.
I remember cleaning house and my
mother cooking,
making sandwiches for everybody.
-So, in a way, they were activists.
-Pretty much.
-Sorry, this is my Aunt Andrea.
-How you doing?
-She's retired General Motors as well.
-Oh, nice. The full crew in here.
Yeah.
-You gonna go back to work?
You gonna get out of retirement?
Oh, they put me out.
-They put you out?
-They put me out.
No, no, I can collect Social Security.
I'm not going back.
It's not like it was.
Her, her husband,
both retired General Motors.
-It's not like it was. How so?
Well, only from what I hear
because I haven't
been in there in a long time.
But everybody's got headphones on now
and they're doing their own thing.
We used to have fun in there.
You joke, you laugh, you…
This is a survivor series.
-You should tell them about…
-I have to say…
Go, Dean.
So, what you see here
are people who went into these workplaces.
And did literally
mind-numbing, very difficult work,
repetitive work, difficult work.
And they didn't lose
their soul in the process.
A lot of folks,
they came out alcoholics, drug addicts.
They maybe didn't come out at all.
These people did.
And they came out
with their spirit and heart intact.
That's not valueless.
That's massive to me personally.
All right, guys.
End of the road today. Flint, Michigan.
Quite an interesting place.
And there's so much
that we didn't get into.
But I want to leave you with a few things.
When a company like GM that pretty much
employs everyone in town
leaves a place like Flint,
the cycle of just a
hard, hard, hard landing happens.
I've seen it all across the country.
And the good thing I would say
from the people we talked to today
is it's reached its bottom.
It might be coming off
that bottom a bit and going up.
It will be interesting to see this place
in 10, 15 years and where it goes.
Maybe it follows Downtown Detroit's story,
which is quite impressive.
Hopefully it does.
And then lastly,
go check out John Hammon.
Yeah, those guys seem so cool.
And I bet the music scene is awesome here.
The good thing that comes
through hard times and strife
is quite often the creatives come out.
And they get to painting
and making beautiful murals
and making awesome music to listen to.
Thank you
for coming along on this journey.
Until the next one.
[soulful music]